Guide to the Alfred and Hortense Wagenknecht and Helen and Carl Winter Family Papers TAM.583
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- II, Helen and Carl Winter Papers
  - III, Political Activities
    - Winter, Carl: "Soviet Union and Real Socialism" [Lecture Notes for Class at Du Bois-Foster School of Marxism Leninism and Related Clip from Moscow News], 1977 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Winter, Carl: "Speech to Colloquium, Arranged by Marxist Institute and Anti-Imperialist Bulletin of FRG", Oct 1978 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Winter, Carl: Speech to National Executive Board of CPUSA on Electoral Politics, Mass Movements and "New Politics" Movement, Apr 1968 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Winter, Carl: Statement of CPUSA in Advance of US-Soviet Summit, circa 1959 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Winter, Carl: Statement to National Committee of CPUSA on Soviet Invasion of Czechoslovakia, Sep 1969 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Winter, Carl: Teaching Materials for National School Class on Socialism, circa 1972 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Winter, Carl [?]: Typed Excerpts from Political Histories by George F. Kennan and Charles Burton Marshall, Undated (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Winter, Carl: "What We Can Learn From the 1930s," Party Affairs, Apr 1971 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Winter, Carl and Allan, William: Draft of an Article for the Michigan Daily Worker on Detroit Mayoral and City Council Elections, Nov 26, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Winter, Carl and Winter, Helen: Mailgram to President Reagan After the Film "The Day After" Protesting Nuclear Deployment, Nov 1983-Dec 1983 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Winter, Helen: 15th Anniversary of Global Books, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Winter, Helen: Cards [General], circa 1970-1979, undated (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Winter, Helen: Cards and Letter From Foreign Embassies and Individuals, 1971-1983, Undated (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Winter, Helen: Chicago Daily Worker Forum: Report on 25th Congress of CPUSA [Notebook and Other Materials], 1976 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Winter, Helen: Clip with Photograph of Helen Winter Leading the 1933 May Day Parade in New York City, circa 1993 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Winter, Helen: Draft of Circular Letter for People's Weekly World, 1990s (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Winter, Helen: "Ford Hunger March Inspired New Struggles," People's Weekly World, Mar 14, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Winter, Helen: International Conference for the Holding of Tripartite Talks for the Peace and Reunification of Korea: Conference Materials and Notes, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - Winter, Helen: "La Politica Exterior De Los Estados Unidos: Como Quisiera Que Fuera Los Trabajadores Norteamericanos" (Journal Article in Spanish), circa 1970-1979 (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Winter, Helen: Memorabilia from Trip to France for Congress of Parti Communiste Francais, May 1979 (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Winter, Helen: Message from the Communist Party, USA [On the Death of Ruth First, African National Congress], Oct 14, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - Winter, Helen: Notes for Radio Moscow "Recollections", Feb 14, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - Winter, Helen: Notes for Speech on Ed Teixeira's 50th Birthday, circa 1982 (Box 8, Folder 36)
    - Winter, Helen: Notes for Speeches on Crisis in Poland and Related Materials, 1982 (Box 8, Folder 37)
    - Winter, Helen: Notes for Speeches on Peace Movement and Foreign Policy, circa 1975-1981 (Box 8, Folder 38)
    - Winter, Helen: Notes from 25th Congress of the CPSU, Feb 1976-Mar 1976 (Box 8, Folder 39)
    - Winter, Helen: Notes from 25th National Convention of CPUSA, Dec 1991 (Box 8, Folder 40)
    - Winter, Helen: Notes from Conference in Sofia, Bulgaria and Questions from Radio Sofia on Georgi Dimitrov, Jun 1982 (Box 8, Folder 41)
    - Winter, Helen: Notes from CPUSA Conference in Washington, DC, Nov 1975 (Box 8, Folder 42)
    - Winter, Helen: Notes on CPUSA Meeting, Feb 15, 1977 (Box 8, Folder 43)
    - Winter, Helen: Notes on Meetings of Delegations of CPUSA and CPSU, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 44)
    - Winter, Helen: Notes on National Alliance Against Racial and Political Repression Rally, April 30, 1993 [Includes Program], May 1, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 45)
    - Winter, Helen: "On the Observance of the 30th Anniversary of the Victory Over Fascism" (Political Affairs or Party Affairs [?]), 1975 (Box 8, Folder 46)
    - Winter, Helen: Printed Materials and Clips Relating to the Peace Movement [New Stockholm Peace Appeal], circa 1975-1977 (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - Winter, Helen: Remarks to Ideological Conference of CPUSA, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 48)
    - Winter, Helen: Speech at Third Annual Dinner of Jewish Affairs, Jan 12, 1975 (Box 8, Folder 49)
    - Winter, Helen: Speech to German Communist Party, Oct 1978 (Box 8, Folder 50)
    - Winter, Helen: "Standards for Party Leadership," Party Affairs [With Letter from Reference Center for Marxist Studies], Jan 1973, Aug 1993 (Box 8, Folder 51)
    - Winter, Helen: "The US People and Foreign Policy" [Draft of Article for World Marxist Review and Correspondence with John Pittman], Dec 1975-Feb 1976 (Box 8, Folder 52)
    - Winter, Helen: World Assembly for Peace and Life, Against Nuclear War, Prague: Conference Materials, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 53)
    - Young, Coleman: Memorial and Obituaries For, 1997 (Box 8, Folder 54)
    - Young Communist League, USA: "Fight the New Right-Wing Congress - An Open Letter to the Youth and Student Movement ...", circa 1990-1999 (Box 8, Folder 55)
    - The Working Woman, March 1933 [Helen Allison on Cover], Mar 1933 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - IV, Smith Act Trials and Defense Work
    Series is comprised of legal documents, clippings, ephemera, writings, notes, and speeches generated and collected between the late-1940s and late-1950s primarily as a result of or related to Carl and Helen Winter’s arrests and trials for violating the Smith Act, and Carl Winter’s imprisonment. Legal documents include texts of opinions and petitions from Carl Winter’s trial, Dennis vs. the United States, in Foley Square, New York, and Helen Winter’s trial with five other leading members of Michigan’s Communist Party, Saul Wellman et. al. vs. the United States of America, between 1953-1954. Includes ephemera from groups opposed to the Smith Act prosecutions including the Civil Rights Congress, Families of the Smith Act Victims, National Association to Win Amnesty for the Smith Act Victims, and the CPUSA.
    Also includes Helen Winter’s steno books from her trial and typescript of her closing remarks; notebooks kept by Carl Winter in prison; a petition by Benjamin Davis against segregation in the prisons; poems, including “A Letter to Carl”; Carl Winter’s speech “12 x 12 Million”; and an apparently unpublished manuscript by Minnesota writer and activist Meridel Le Sueur entitled “Double Jeopardy” on the plight of families of Smith Act defendants. A comprehensive collection of clippings of press coverage from Detroit’s tabloid press of Helen Winter’s trial comprises a significant part of the series.
    - "The Amnesty Campaign" [4 Page Memo to National Committee to Win Amnesty for Smith Act Victims, Author Unknown], circa Jun 1953 (Box 8, Folder 57)
    - Amter, Sadie Van Veen: "Women Courageous (Certain Lines for Helen Winter and Esther Jackson and Edna Winston)", circa 1953 (Box 8, Folder 58)
    - Bachrach, Marion: Amnesty [With Attached Letter Signed by Six Michigan Smith Act Defendants], 1953 (Box 8, Folder 59)
    - Bloor, Ella Reeve: "Salute to the Wives of the Twelve Leaders" [3 page TS], circa 1949 (Box 8, Folder 60)
    - Cattmar, Nell: "Millions of People Will Help Little Michele" [Letter to Helen Winter], circa 1955 (Box 8, Folder 61)
    - Civil Rights Congress [New York], circa 1949-1954 (Box 8, Folder 62)
    - Civil Rights Congress [Pittsburgh]: Pamphlet on Steve Nelson and Pennsylvania Smith Act Defendants, circa 1953 (Box 8, Folder 63)
    - Civil Rights Congress of Illinois [Claude Lightfoot], 1954 (Box 8, Folder 64)
    - Civil Rights Congress of Los Angeles: CRC Bulletin, Apr 1952 (Box 8, Folder 65)
    - Civil Rights Congress of Michigan [Smith Act Fight Back Campaign and Labor Defender], circa 1948-1955 (Box 8, Folder 66)
    - Clippings: Smith Act Trial of Carl Winter, April 1948-October 1949, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - Clippings: Smith Act Trial of Carl Winter, Feb. 27, 1955, Mar. 2, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 82)
    - Clippings: Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter, Mar 1952-Sep 1952 (Box 8, Folder 68)
    - Clippings: Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter, Oct 1952 (Box 8, Folder 69)
    - Clippings: Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter, Mar 1953, Sep 1953 (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - Clippings: Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter, Oct 1953 (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - Clippings: Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter, Nov 1, 1953-Nov 15, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - Clippings: Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter, Nov 16, 1953-Nov 30, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - Clippings: Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter, Dec 1, 1953-Dec 15, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - Clippings: Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter, Dec 16, 1953-Dec 29, 1953 (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - Clippings: Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter, Jan 1954 (Box 8, Folder 76)
    - Clippings: Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter, Feb 1, 1954-Feb 15, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 77)
    - Clippings: Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter, Feb 16, 1954-Mar 1954 (Box 8, Folder 78)
    - Clippings: Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter, Aug 1958-Oct 1958 (Box 8, Folder 79)
    - Clippings: Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter, Undated (Box 8, Folder 80)
    - Clippings: Smith Act Trials, circa 1950-1959 (Box 8, Folder 81)
    - Clippings [Oversize]: Smith Act Trial of Carl Winter, 1948-1949 (Oversize 11, Folder 1)
    - Clippings [Oversize]: Labor Defender: Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter, 1953-1954 (Oversize 11, Folder 2)
    - Clippings [Oversize]: Smith Act of Helen Winter, Sep 1952-Oct 1952 (Oversize 11, Folder 3)
    - Clippings [Oversize]: Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter, Sep 1953-Nov 1953 (Oversize 11, Folder 4)
    - Clippings [Oversize]: Smith Act Trial of Helen Winter, Dec 1953-Feb 1954 (Oversize 11, Folder 5)
    - Committee to Keep McCarthyism Out of Michigan by Fighting Smith Act Persecutions [Civil Rights Congress], Dec 1953-Jan 1954 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Communist Party USA: Newsletter Containing Copy of Indictment of Twelve Communist Leaders, circa 1949 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Communist Party USA National Education Commission: "Outline on New Stage in Struggle for Peace" [Discussion Material], May 1953 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Connecticut Volunteers for Civil Rights, circa 1954 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Crockett, George: "Memorandum Re: Second Indictment" [of Carl Winter], Jan 22, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Crockett, George [As Agent for Hortense Allison]: Receipt for Bond for Carl Winter, Mar 1, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Davis, Benjamin J. vs. Herbert Brownell, Attorney General of the United States and James Bennett, Director of the Bureau of Prisons: Petition Against Segregation in Prisons, circa 1950-1954 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Dennis, Eugene et al. vs. United States of America: Full Text Supreme Court Opinions in the Case of the Communist Leaders June 4, 1951 [Annotated by Carl Winter], circa 1950-1954 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Dennis, Eugene et al. vs. USA: Motion for Leave to File Supplemental Petition for Rehearing and Supplemental Petition, Sep 27, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Dennis, Eugene et al. vs. USA: Petition for Leave to File and Memorandum of Amici Curiae in Support of Petition for Rehearing, Sep 27, 1951 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Dennis, Eugene et al. vs. USA: Petition of Defendants to the Honorable Judge Harold R. Medina, Mar 11, 1949 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Dennis, Peggy: Memo on Parole Petition for Smith Act Prisoners, circa 1950-1959 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Draft of Article for Press on Denial of Parole for Carl Winter and Other Communist Leaders [Revisions by Helen Winter], circa 1953 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Essay on Response of American Public to Smith Act and Anticommunist Measures (3 pgs.; Author Unknown), Jun 30, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Families of the Smith Act Victims (Michigan): Circulars, Press Release, Correspondence and Ephemera, 1952-1954 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Families of the Smith Act Victims (Michigan): Hortense Allison's Notes On, 1952-1954 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Families of the Smith Act Victims (National): Press Releases, Newsletters, Circulars, Summary of Proceedings from National Meeting and Other Ephemera, 1952-1954 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Fehlhaber, Elmer: "The Dialectic of Providence" [15 pp. TS Dedicated to Detroit Smith Act Defendants], Jan 12, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Gordon, David: "A Letter to Carl" [Two Typescripts of Poem], circa 1951-1953 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Gordon, David: "Paul Robeson and Other Poems" [47 pp. MSS; Includes "A Letter to Carl"], Dec 1951 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Harlien, Mary Ann: Notes for United Press Article on Helen Winter, circa 1953-1954 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Le Sueur, Meridel: "Double Jeopardy" [?] [TS for Pamphlet on Families of Smith and McCarran Act Victims with Edits by Helen Winter and Anna Ganley, 39 pp], circa 1953 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Michigan Committee for Protection of the Foreign Born, 1953-1955 (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Michigan Council for Peace: News of Peace Newsletter, Flyer on Korean War, Jan 1953 (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Michigan Committee to Win Amnesty for Smith Act Victims [Carl Haessler], circa 1952-1953 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - Michigan Smith Act Defendants: Holiday Cards, circa 1950-1959 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Michigan Smith Act Defendants and Families Committee: Latest Facts on the Appeal to the Supreme Court Against Michigan Smith Act Convictions, Mar 1956 (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Michigan Smith Act Trial: List of Exhibits, circa 1954 (Box 9, Folder 28)
    - Michigan State Committee of the Communist Party: "For Defending Your Rights ... This Man Got 30 Days in Jail" [Carl Winter], 1948 (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - Minnesota Committee for Amnesty for the Smith Act Victims [Meridel Le Sueur]: Circular and Event Announcement, Jul 1952-Aug 1952 (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - Miscellaneous Smith Act Trial Materials, circa 1950-1959 (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - National Committee to Win Amnesty for Smith Act Victims, 1952-1953 (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - Oral Argument of Dorothy Forest in Support of Motion to Dismiss the Indictment Against St. Louis Smith Act Defendants, Apr 17, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - Organizing Committee for Prisoners Welfare Committee [Michigan]: Invitation to Social Evening and Birthday for Carl Winter, circa 1950-1954 (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - People's Conference to Repeal the McCarran Act: Petition to Congress to Repeal the McCarran Act, circa 1954 (Box 9, Folder 35)
    - Political Victim's Welfare Committee: Pamphlet on Chicago Smith Act Victims [Lilian Green and Doris Fine], circa 1950-1959 (Box 9, Folder 36)
    - "Problem Offenders" [1 pg TS on Communist Prisoners, Author Unknown], circa 1950-1959 (Box 9, Folder 37)
    - Provisional Committee for Amnesty for Benjamin J. Davis, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 38)
    - Provisional Trade Union Committee for Repeal of the Smith Act, circa 1952 (Box 9, Folder 39)
    - Sacher, Harry: Press Release with Attached Letter to US Attorney General Protesting Discrimination Against African American Prisoners [Benjamin Davis], Oct 1951 (Box 9, Folder 40)
    - "Some Legal Questions" [2 pp TS, Author Unknown], circa 1953-1954 (Box 9, Folder 41)
    - Song Lyrics About McCarthyism and Smith Act Trials [Some by Helen Travis], circa 1950-1959 (Box 9, Folder 42)
    - Sugar, Maurice: Invitation to Discussion on Smith Act, circa 1950-1959 (Box 9, Folder 43)
    - UAW-CIO (Michigan): Letters in Support of Michigan Smith Act Defendants from Amalgamated Local 351 and Ford Local 600, Feb 13, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 44)
    - UAW-CIO 14th Convention: Resolutions Against Smith Act and in Support of Amnesty, circa 1953 (Box 9, Folder 45)
    - United States District Court, Eastern District of Michigan: Notice of Opening of Smith Act Trial on October 13, 1953, Aug 28, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 46)
    - United States of America vs. William Z. Foster, et al.: Election Not to Serve Sentence Imposed, circa 1948-1949 (Box 9, Folder 47)
    - USA vs. Saul Laurence Wellman et al., 1953-1954 (Box 9, Folder 48)
    - USA vs. Carl Winter: Legal Documents [Includes Transcript of Proceedings], 1948-1956 (Box 9, Folder 49)
    - United States of America vs. Helen Mary Winter: Transcript of Proceedings on September 18, 1952, Sep 18, 1952 (Box 9, Folder 50)
    - Wellman, Peggy: Letter of Appeal to Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, Feb 26, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 51)
    - Wellman, Saul, Nat Ganley, Tom Dennis, Billy Allan, Phil Schatz and Helen Winter: "Greetings From Smith Act Defendants", circa Feb 1954 (Box 9, Folder 52)
    - Wellman, Saul Laurence et al. vs. United States of America: Appelants Supplemental Brief, Mar 2, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 53)
    - Wellman, Saul Laurence et al. vs. USA: Brief for Appellants [Filed by George Crockett and Ernest Goodman], circa 1954 (Box 9, Folder 54)
    - Wellman, Saul Laurence et al. vs. USA: Memorandum for the Government, circa 1954 (Box 9, Folder 55)
    - Wellman, Saul Laurence, et al. vs. USA: Motion to Proceed Forma Pauperis and Petition for Writ of Certiorari to the US Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit, circa 1956 (Box 9, Folder 56)
    - Wellman, Saul Laurence, et al. vs. USA: Notice to Dismiss Indictment and Cancel Bond, circa 1958 (Box 9, Folder 57)
    - Wellman, Saul Laurence, et al. vs. USA: On a Petition for a Writ of Certiorari to the US Court of Appeals for the Sixth Circuit: Memorandum for the US, Feb 1956 (Box 9, Folder 58)
    - Wellman, Saul Laurence, et al. vs. USA: Order of Judge Frank Picard to Dismiss Indictment, Sep 16, 1958 (Box 9, Folder 59)
    - Wellman, Saul Laurence, et al. vs. USA: Petit Jury Panel, Oct 6, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 60)
    - Wellman, Saul Laurence, et al. vs. USA: Summary of the Activities of Helen Winter Drawn from Larger Government Document (19 pp), circa 1954 (Box 9, Folder 61)
    - Wellman, Saul Laurence, et al. vs. USA: Court's Decision on Appeal [US Court of Appeals], Nov 18, 1955 (Box 9, Folder 62)
    - Wellman, Saul Laurence, Thomas Dennis and Nat Ganley: Petition to Frank Picard to Voluntarily Dismiss Himself as Judge, Oct 21, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 63)
    - Winter, Carl: "12 Times 12 Million" [Speech to National Committee of CPUSA], Dec 9, 1948 (Box 9, Folder 64)
    - Winter, Carl: Belongings Seized At Time of Arrest (List of) and "Crockett - 2/14.49 Examination of Carl Winter's Papers - At US District Courthouse", Jul 20, 1948, Feb 14, 1949 (Box 9, Folder 65)
    - Winter, Carl: Correspondence Course Materials (Auto Technician) and Diploma in Toolmaking, circa 1951-1956 (Box 9, Folder 66)
    - Winter, Carl: Legal Services Agreement with George Crockett, Dec 9, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 67)
    - Winter, Carl: Notebook and Notes, Jul 1951-1955 (Box 9, Folder 68)
    - Winter, Carl: Notes Relating to Trial, Dec 31, 1952, Feb 6, 1953, Undated (Box 9, Folder 69)
    - Winter, Carl: Notice of Warrant from United States Marshal, Southern District of NY; Notice of Detainer from United States Marshal, Topeka, Kansas, Mar 29, 1954, Oct 8, 1954 (Box 9, Folder 70)
    - Winter, Carl: Parole, Documents Relating to (Including Certificate of Conditional Release), Dec 1952-Mar 1955 (Box 9, Folder 71)
    - Winter, Carl: Press Release on Forty-Sixth Birthday Celebration With Letters from Bill McKie, Maurice Sugar and Bob Travis, Sep 1952 (Box 9, Folder 72)
    - Winter, Carl: Prison Administration Forms and Newsletters, circa 1952-1954 (Box 9, Folder 73)
    - Winter, Carl: Prison Envelopes [Marked With Tally of Correspondence With Family and Attorneys], circa 1951-circa 1954 (Box 9, Folder 74)
    - Winter, Carl: Prison Receipts and Accounting, 1951-1954 (Box 9, Folder 75)
    - Winter, Carl: "Proposed Line for Smith Act Defense" [Interview; 5 pp], Jun 18, 1949 (Box 9, Folder 76)
    - Winter, Carl: Subscription to Civil Rights Congress [Copy; Used as Exhibit], Jun 30, 1950 (Box 9, Folder 77)
    - Winter, Helen: Accounting Notebook, 1952-1954 (Box 9, Folder 78)
    - Winter, Helen: Appeal to Have Carl Winter Transferred to Prison in Milan, Michigan, Oct 1953-Nov 1953 (Box 9, Folder 79)
    - Winter, Helen: Description of Arrest Of (TS, 1 pg), Undated (Box 9, Folder 80)
    - Winter, Helen: Draft of Article on Helen Winter's Illness and Smith Act Trial, circa 1954 (Box 9, Folder 81)
    - Winter, Helen: Letter to the Editor of the Daily Worker [Draft], circa 1950-1959 (Box 9, Folder 82)
    - Winter, Helen: Notes and Speeches from Amnesty Campaign for Carl Winter and Others, circa 1952 (Box 9, Folder 83)
    - Winter, Helen: Notes for Remarks at Dinner to Support Parole and Amnesty for Henry Winston and Gilbert Green, circa 1955-1956 (Box 9, Folder 84)
    - Winter, Helen: Notes From Michigan Smith Act Trial, Including Draft of Final Statement to Judge Frank Picard, circa Oct 1953- Feb 1954 (Box 9, Folder 85)
    - Winter, Helen: "Overt Acts" [Document from Michigan Smith Act Trial], circa Oct 1953-Feb 1954 (Box 9, Folder 86)
    - Winter, Helen: Parole Appeal for Carl Winter, Feb 1953-Mar 1953 (Box 9, Folder 87)
    - Winter, Helen: Stenobooks From the Smith Act Trial, Nov 1953-Dec 1953 (Box 9, Folder 88)
    - Winter, Helen: Stenobooks From the Smith Act Trial, Dec 1953-Jan 1954 (Box 9, Folder 89)
    - Winter, Helen: Typescript of Closing Remarks of Billy Allan (Incomplete) and Helen Winter from Smith Act Trial, Feb 1954 (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - V, Photographs
    This series includes negatives, black and white prints, and color prints of Carl and Helen Winter's political and professional activities, including events they attended, trips overseas on behalf of the CPUSA, campaigns and protests, as well as family photographs and portraits of CPUSA leaders. Photographs primarily document political and professional activities on behalf of the CPUSA and the Daily World, which Carl Winter edited, and include trips in the 1960s and 1970s to Mongolia, Romania, Germany, and France to cover the French General Strike in 1968, and photographs taken inside the Daily World offices in New York City. Includes several photographs and negatives, apparently taken for the Detroit News, of Carl and Helen Winter at the Leon Mosely demonstration in Detroit in June 1948. Family photographs are included in Carl Winter's memorial album. Prominent individuals and CPUSA leaders appearing in the photographs include James Jackson, Henry Winston, Benjamin Davis, Ollie Harrington, and Yevgeni Yevtushenko.
    Approximately thirty 4 x 5 negatives were separated from the Detroit Police Department Red Squad Files in Series III: Political Activities, and document demonstrations outside the Foley Square Courthouse in New York City on August 15, 1949 during the Smith Act trial of Carl Winter (Dennis vs. United States).
    - Allison, Hortense -- Jobs Now Rally, Apr 1975-Jun 1975 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Bogota, Columbia [Prints and Negatives], circa Dec 1971 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Carl Winter Memorial Album, circa 1924-1991 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Carl Winter Memorial Plaque, circa 1991 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Civil Rights Congress Protest, Jun 1950 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - CPUSA [Includes Portraits of Leaders], circa 1930-1939, circa 1980-1989 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Dennis-Allan-Goldman Campaign, circa 1980-1989 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Detroit Police Department Red Squad Files on Carl Winter: Demonstrations, Foley Square, New York City [Negatives], Aug 15, 1949 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - French General Strike [Near Paris], Jun 4, 1968 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Germany, circa 1970-1979 (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Helen Winter -- Smith Act Trial, circa 1953-1954 (Box 10, Folder 11)